<?xml version="1.0"?>
<text>
<title>Labor Migration in Israel</title>
<paragraph>
Overseas labor migration is a relatively new phenomenon in Israeli society. Until the end of the 1980s Palestinian daily commuters from the West Bank and the Gaza Strip comprised almost seven percent of the entire Israeli labor force. They were recruited after the 1967 Six-Day War to perform mostly menial, low-status, manual jobs in the secondary sector of the economy, mainly in construction, agriculture, and services.
</paragraph>
<paragraph>
The outbreak of the first Intifada (Palestinian uprising) in 1987 created a shortage of labor in low-status positions when the entry of non-citizen Palestinian workers into Israel was prevented because of imposed closure or self-imposed strikes. These events, coupled with strong pressure exerted by employers in the construction and agriculture sectors, set in motion the process which has led to the massive organized recruitment of overseas labor migrants since the early 1990s.
</paragraph>
<paragraph>
Since then, the share of foreign workers in the Israeli labor market has grown constantly and rapidly. Whereas in 1993 migrant workers comprised only 1.6 percent of the Israeli labor force, by the end of 2012 their share increased to 11 percent, placing Israel at the top of the industrialized economies most heavily dependent on foreign labor. According to Israel’s Central Bureau of Statistics, the total number of foreign workers residing in Israel in 2012 was close to 300,000 (166,500 with a work permit, 133,500 without). Overseas labor migrants were formally recruited for three main sectors: construction (in the 1990s mainly from Romania and Turkey, but currently mainly from China), agriculture (from Thailand), and domestic caregiving (mainly from the Philippines, but lately also from India, Nepal, Sri Lanka, and Moldova).
</paragraph>
<paragraph>
(Labor migrant recruitment practices in Israel; Rebeca Raijman and Nonna Kushnirovich, Ruppin Academic Center, March 2012. Stats updated from the Israeli Central Bureau of Statistics)
</paragraph>
<title>Asylum Seekers in Israel</title>
<paragraph>
In recent years, there has been a sharp increase in the arrival of asylum seekers in Israel. According to data from the Population, Immigration and Border Authority from August 2012, the number of "infiltrators" living in Israel stands at approximately 57,000 people. An estimated 15,210 of these are from Sudan, 35,895 are from Eritrea and 6,000 from other African countries. "Infiltrators" enter Israel via the Sinai desert by crossing the Egypt-Israel border. 
</paragraph>
<paragraph>
Colloquially, the term "infiltrators" is used by the Israeli public to refer to African migrants who cross the Sinai desert and enter Israel from its southern border with Egypt. Legally, this term is defined in the Prevention of Infiltration Law, 1954 (amended in 2012), as "anyone who is not a resident…, who entered Israel not via one of the recognized border stations." The term does not address the individual's reason for entering Israel and hence does not distinguish between economic migrants, refugees and individuals with criminal or terroristic intent. 
</paragraph>
<paragraph>
In Israel, there is no way of knowing for certain who is a refugee and who is not. The Ministry of Interior refuses to individually assess applications for asylum of Sudanese and Eritrean nationals. Accusations that Africans in Israel are "work infiltrators" are used to incite negative public opinion. Data from a number of other countries, however, can offer an indication as to the potential status of these individuals. 
</paragraph>
<paragraph>
Eritreans and Sudanese, who comprise 90% of this population in Israel, receive relatively high recognition rates as refugees around the world (both UNHCR and Amnesty International have reported grave human rights violations in Sudan and Eritrea and recommended that asylum seekers not be returned there). The rate of refugee status recognition for Eritrean asylum seekers is 88% and for Sudanese 64%. However, the current rate of refugee status recognition in Israel is 0.2%.
</paragraph>
<link>http://www.asylumseekers.org/about-asylum-seekers-in-israel.html</link>
<link>http://www.hotline.org.il</link>
</text>	